<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='http://blogawesome.com/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<title>
My Awesome Blog
</title>
<link>
http://blogawesome.com/
</link>
<description>
This blog is awesome
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Wed, 10 Jun 2015 15:04:10 +0200
</lastBuildDate>
<item>
<guid>
http://blogawesome.com/blog/posts/2015-06-10-init.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blogawesome.com/blog/posts/2015-06-10-init.html
</link>
<title>
(init blog)
</title>
<description>
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;about&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;About&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is my blog. I haven't really blogged ever. I so far did not think that I have something interesting to say. Given my experience at several customers and the work I am doing there I feel it might be different at least for them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So why am I blogging then? Two things are of interest to me personally: one, I can express my opinions about different matters in a written form with more time to actually formulate my points rather than in a heated discussion. In these discussions I usually don't talk too much as I really hate being interrupted. Take aside that this is really bad behaviour during discussions I often see this and rather get me out of this as soon as possible; usually these are pointless and will not lead anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, I hope to make it a habit in order to get stuff out of my head.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main topics on this blog will be information retrieval, software architecture, programming languages and agile methods. I am a professional software developer for eight years now working in the fields of information retrieval and machine learning. I stopped counting the number of projects I was involved in but the number of customers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;a field I am professionally working in for eight years now&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Wed, 10 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0200
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
