<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mgmt on all things considered...</title>
    <link>https://truemped.github.io/tags/mgmt/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mgmt on all things considered...</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 09:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://truemped.github.io/tags/mgmt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My first year in Management</title>
      <link>https://truemped.github.io/posts/2019/04/first-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://truemped.github.io/posts/2019/04/first-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About a year ago I transitioned into management. I changed my role from Senior&#xA;Software Developer to Engineering Lead in Zalando. In this post I want to share&#xA;my experience, good and bad, things that went well, where I screwed up and what&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m taking from it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-difficult-first-year&#34;&gt;&#xA;  A difficult first year&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;heading-link&#34; href=&#34;#a-difficult-first-year&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;i class=&#34;fa-solid fa-link&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34; title=&#34;Link to heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&#xA;    &lt;span class=&#34;sr-only&#34;&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As my manager put it in my performance review: the last year was one of my most&#xA;challenging ones. And he was right. In theory my game plan was pretty &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt;:&#xA;I became Engineering Lead for the team I was an engineer before. A well&#xA;functioning and I might say one of the most high performing teams I&amp;rsquo;ve ever&#xA;worked in. It did not take long though until the team dissolved itself. For one&#xA;member it was clear from the beginning that he would leave. But it did not take&#xA;long until the next engineer from this team said he would leave the company.&#xA;This was a real setback because I value him tremendously as an engineer and&#xA;enjoyed the interactions we had. Sadly he had made up his mind even before I&#xA;became manager and for me there was no way to keep him. Back then and still&#xA;today I was not under the impression that it was because of my transition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
